The first motion picture in CinemaScope--the modern
miracle you see without glasses!
The Robe is a drama, history film directed by Henry Koster.
Drunk and disillusioned Roman, Marcellus Gallio, wins Jesus'
robe in a dice game after the crucifixion.
Marcellus has never been a man of faith like his slave, Demetrius, but when Demetrius escapes with
the robe, Marcellus experiences disturbing visions and feels guilty for his actions.
Convinced that destroying the robe will cure him, Marcellus sets out to find
Demetrius — and discovers his Christian faith along the way.
Marcellus Gallio, played by Richard Burton.
Diana, played by Jean Simmons.
Demetrius, played by Victor Mature.
Pontius Pilate, played by Richard Boone.
Abidor, played by Leon Askin.
Peter, played by Michael Rennie.
The Robe is a 1953 American  Biblical epic film that tells the story of a Roman military
tribune who commands the unit that is responsible for the crucifixion of Jesus.
The film was released by 20th Century Fox and was the first film
released in the widescreen process CinemaScope.
Like other early CinemaScope films, The Robe was shot with Henri
Chrétien's original Hypergonar anamorphic lenses.
The film was directed by Henry Koster and produced by Frank Ross.
The screenplay was adapted from Lloyd C.
Douglas's 1942 novel by Gina Kaus, Albert Maltz, and Philip Dunne—although Maltz's place among the
blacklisted Hollywood 10 led to his being denied his writing credit for many years.
The score was composed by Alfred Newman, and the
cinematography was by Leon Shamroy.
The film stars Richard Burton, Jean Simmons, Victor Mature and Michael Rennie, and
co-stars Jay Robinson, Dean Jagger, Torin Thatcher, Richard Boone, Betta St.
John, Jeff Morrow, Ernest Thesiger, and others.
A sequel, Demetrius and the Gladiators (1954),
continues from where The Robe ends.
The film explores themes of palestine, roman empire,
christianity, crucifixion, bible.
The tone is dark and emotional.